<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://syriaca.org/documentation/syriaca-tei-main.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xd="http://www.oxygenxml.com/ns/doc/xsl" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" xml:lang="en">Bao'en Monastery <foreign xml:lang="zh-Hant">報恩寺</foreign>
            </title>
            <title level="m">Architectura Sinica</title>
            <principal>Tracy Miller</principal>
            <editor role="general" xml:id="TGM">Tracy Miller</editor>
            <editor role="creator" xml:id="ZYY">ZOU Yuyang</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Website coordination by</resp>
               <name type="person" xml:id="YFB">Yuh-Fen Benda</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial research 2021 by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="#ZYY">ZOU Yuyang</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.0"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Architectura Sinica</authority>
            <idno type="URI">https://architecturasinica.org/place/000293/tei</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2021-04-05-04:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
            <language ident="zh-latn-pinyin">Pinyin</language>
            <language ident="zh-Hant">Traditional Chinese</language>
            <language ident="zh-Hans">Simplified Chinese</language>
            <language ident="zh-latn-wadegile">Wade-Giles</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change n="1.0" who="#ZYY" when="2021-04-05">CREATED: place record</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <listPlace>
            <place xml:id="place-000293" type="site">
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-1" type="site-name" xml:lang="en">Great Bao'en Monastery</placeName>
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-4" type="site-name" xml:lang="zh-Hant">大報恩寺</placeName>
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-5" type="site-name" xml:lang="zh-Hans">大报恩寺</placeName>
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-5" type="site-name" xml:lang="zh-latn-pinyin">Changgansi</placeName>
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-6" type="alternate" xml:lang="zh-Hant">長干寺</placeName>
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-7" type="alternate" xml:lang="zh-Hans">长干寺</placeName>
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-5" type="site-name" xml:lang="zh-latn-pinyin">Jianchusi</placeName>
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-6" type="alternate" xml:lang="zh-Hant">建初寺</placeName>
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-7" type="alternate" xml:lang="zh-Hans">建初寺</placeName>
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-5" type="site-name" xml:lang="zh-latn-pinyin">Tianxisi</placeName>
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-6" type="alternate" xml:lang="zh-Hant">天禧寺</placeName>
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-7" type="alternate" xml:lang="zh-Hans">天禧寺</placeName>  
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-5" type="site-name" xml:lang="zh-latn-pinyin">Ci'en</placeName>
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-6" type="alternate" xml:lang="zh-Hant">慈恩旌忠寺</placeName>
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-7" type="alternate" xml:lang="zh-Hans">慈恩旌忠寺</placeName>
            
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-2" type="site-name" xml:lang="zh-latn-pinyin">Dàbàoēnsì</placeName>
               <placeName xml:id="name000293-3" type="site-name" xml:lang="zh-latn-wadegile">Ta-pao-en-szu</placeName>
               <idno type="URI">https://architecturasinica.org/place/000293</idno>
               <desc type= "site-data" xml:lang="en" source="bibl000293-2">Located outside the Zhonghuamen 中華門 in Qinhuai District 秦淮區, Nanjing, Jiangsu, Bao’en Monastery is the oldest Buddhist site in Nanjing and potentially the earliest Buddhist complex in Southern China. Although none of the historic buildings are extant, in 2015 the excavated site was turned into a museum. 
                  
                  The monastery’s origins are usually traced to the <term ref="/keyword/k000094"> Sun Wu Kingdom (222-280) </term> and may have included an Asoka pagoda and a small nun’s jingshe 精舍 (“refinement chamber” or convent), but all were destroyed with the fall of the Wu. Likely reconstructed in the <term ref="/keyword/k000091"> Western Jin </term>, the site gained even greater fame when the monk Liu Sahe 劉薩訶 (Huida 慧达, 3rd-4th cen. CE), following a strange qi emanating from Changgan Ward, discovered a reliquary deposit reputed to be one of Asoka’s original 84,000 reliquaries, nineteen of which had been transmitted to the far east. The complex was expanded by Emperor Wu of Liang (r. 502-549), who is said to have excavated the relics and reinterred them in a pair of pagodas. Although the official name of the monastery at the time was likely “Asoka Monastery” (Ayuwangsi 阿育王寺) it was commonly referred to by the name Changgan Monastery (Changgansi長干寺), after its location in Changgan Ward (Nanjing shi Kaogu yanjiusuo 2015, 4; Nanshi 78.1955).
                  
                  Having burned in the Sui-Tang wars, the site became a military camp during the <term ref="/keyword/k000082"> Tang dynasty </term>. With the support of Song Zhenzong during the <term ref="/keyword/k000055">Dazhong xiangfu reign period (1008-1017) </term>. The monk Kezheng可政 restored Changgan Monastery on its original site and built a new nine-story brick pagoda originally named True (or Perfected) Body Pagoda (Zhenshen ta 真身塔). To honor the site Zhenzong bestowed a plaque with the name Tianxi Monastery in the second year of the Tianxi reign period (1018), and renamed the pagoda “Relic Pagoda of Sagacious Influence” (Shenggan shelita 聖感舍利塔.) The monastery was further given the title Tianxi Doctrinal Monastery of Compassionate Blessings and Manifest Loyalty (Tianxi ci’en jingzhongsi天禧慈恩旌忠教寺) during the <term ref="/keyword/k000101">Yuan dynasty</term>, but although it was renovated at the beginning of the <term ref=""/keyword/k000051>Ming</term>, it burned again in 1408 (Nanjing shi Kaogu yanjiusuo, 4-6).
                  
                  In 1412, the Yongle Emperor (Zhu Di 朱棣 r. 1402-1424) ordered the monastery to be rebuilt in full accordance with the architectural scale and standards of the imperial palace (Nanjing shi Kaogu yanjiusuo, 4-6). Dedicated to the imperial family, the Yongle Emperor renamed it the Great Bao’en Monastery (大报恩寺; (Monastery for Repaying Kindness)) in gratitude to his parents (Jing and Hu 2002, 36). The massive construction project, said to have been supervised by Zheng He 鄭和, took nineteen years to finish (Jing and Hu 2002, 36). The most famous building in the monastery was the Bao’en Monastery Pagoda, which was covered by colored glaze tiles liuliwa 琉璃瓦 and housed important Buddhist relics, themselves held within a Seven Treasures Asoka pagoda七寶阿育王塔. Known in the West as the “Porcelain Pagoda,” the Bao’ensi Pagoda came to be regarded as one of the Wonders of the World (Campbell 2020, 16-17). Over the Ming dynasty, ten major sects of Buddhism all had lectures in the monastery and the monastery was also in charge of engraving and printing the Nanzang南藏 (Ren and Yang 1989, 117). In the fourth year of the Xianfeng reign period (1854), during the Taiping Rebellion, the monastery was unfortunately destroyed by fire (Jing and Hu 2002, 38). Only one hall, two dragon-tortoise stele bases (guifu 龜趺 or bixi 贔屭), and the Da Bao’ensi stele survived (Ren and Yang 1989, 117). 
                  
                  Differing from conventional north-south orientation, the Ming dynasty building complex was oriented east-west, with the main ritual buildings located in the north and the subsidiary buildings in the south. The main northern zone originally consisted of over twenty halls (Ren and Yang 1989, 117). On the central axis, from west to east, there were the Jingang Hall 金剛殿, Xiangshuihe Bridge 香水河橋, Celestial Kings Hall 天王殿, main hall大殿, <term ref="/place/000293a">Glazed Pagoda 琉璃塔</term>, Guanyin Hall 觀音殿 and Dharma Hall 法堂. Framing the courtyards on the north and south were two stele pavilions, sutra repositories, a Patriarch Hall 祖師堂 and Vihara Hall 伽藍殿. The extensive southern precinct included further sutra repositories and the abbot’s quarters (fangzhang方丈) (Nanjing shi Kaogu yanjiusuo, 4-6).
                  
                  In preparation for the creation of a Great Bao’en Monastery Site Park, the Nanjing archaeological bureau excavated the entire northern complex from 2007-2010. In 2007 the pagoda foundation and the <term ref="/place/000293b">Underground Palace 地宮 </term> were excavated(Nanjing kaogu yanjiusuo 2015, 6). In 2008 a bone relic of Sakyamuni and a variety of valuable Buddhist cultural relics were excavated from the reliquary deposit (Leng 2016, 56). Inscriptions in the reliquary deposit indicate that this was from the Song period reinternment of the Changgan Monastery relics.
                  
                  In 2015, led by a multidisciplinary team from Southeast University, the Great Bao’ensi Site Museum 大報恩寺遺址博物館 was constructed on the original site of the historical temple (Chen 2017, 1). The architectural plan of the museum presents the temple’s general layout during the Ming Dynasty (Han 2017, 12). Retaining the original central axis, the current outer walls and galleries form a rectangular courtyard that emulates the historical temple in terms of scale (Han 2017, 12). The museum therefore serves to shelter and connect the fragmented and scattered authentic ruins of the monastery and at the same time display the cultural relics within the grand layout of the royal temple(Chen 2017, 6).
               </desc>
               <state type="existence" subtype="dynasty" source="#bibl000293-1" from="1368-01-01"
                  to="1644-01-01">
                  <label>Dynasty</label>
                  <desc>Ming 1368-1644</desc>
               </state>
               <note type="External Links">
                  <p>
                     <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porcelain_Tower_of_Nanjing">Wikipedia (in English)</ref>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <ref target="https://tinyurl.com/uszw7s">Wikipedia (in Chinese)</ref>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <ref target="https://tinyurl.com/444f3cdy">百度百科</ref>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <location type="nested">
                  <country>China</country>
                  <region type="province">
                     <placeName xml:lang="en">Jiangsu province</placeName>
                     <placeName xml:lang="zh-Hant">江蘇省</placeName>
                     <placeName xml:lang="zh-latn-pinyin">Jiāngsū shěng</placeName>
                  </region>
                  <region type="county-city">
                     <placeName xml:lang="en">Nanjing Municipality</placeName>
                     <placeName xml:lang="zh-Hant">南京市</placeName>
                     <placeName xml:lang="zh-latn-pinyin">Nánjīng shì</placeName>
                  </region>
                  <region type="political-subdivision">
                     <placeName xml:lang="en">Qinhuai District</placeName>
                     <placeName xml:lang="zh-Hant">秦淮區</placeName>
                     <placeName xml:lang="zh-latn-pinyin">Qínhuái qū</placeName>
                  </region>
               </location>
               <location type="gps" subtype="preferred">
                  <geo>32.011991 118.776955</geo>
                  <note>geolocation taken from GoogleEarth</note>
               </location>
               <trait type="type" sub-type="site type">
                  <label>Type</label>
                  <desc xml:lang="en">monastery (Buddhist)</desc>
                  <desc xml:lang="zh-latn-pinyin">si</desc>
                  <desc xml:lang="zh-Hant">寺</desc>
                  <desc xml:lang="zh-Hans">寺</desc>
               </trait>
               <bibl xml:id="bibl000293-1">
                  <ptr target="https://architecturasinica.org/bibl/ZBKKJWX7"/>
                  <citedRange unit="pp">12</citedRange>
               </bibl>
            </place>
            <listRelation>
               <relation active="https://architecturasinica.org/place/000293" passive="https://architecturasinica.org/keyword/k000052" ref="dcterms:subject" ana="site-type"/>
               <relation active="https://architecturasinica.org/place/000293" ref="dcterms:temporal" passive="https://architecturasinica.org/keyword/k000051" ana="dynasty"/>
            </listRelation>
         </listPlace>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>