<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../taxonomy.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xd="http://www.oxygenxml.com/ns/doc/xsl" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" xml:lang="zh-latn-pinyin">
               <foreign xml:lang="zh-Hant">塔</foreign> tǎ</title>
            <title level="m">Architectura Sinica</title>
            <principal>Tracy Miller</principal>
            <editor role="creator">Tracy Miller</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person">Tracy Miller</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.0"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Architectura Sinica</authority>
         	<idno type="URI">https://architecturasinica.org/keyword/k000060/tei</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2018-03-21</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
            <language ident="zh-latn-pinyin">Pinyin</language>
            <language ident="zh-latn-pinyin-nt">Pinyin without tones</language>
            <language ident="zh-latn-wadegile">Wade-Giles</language>
            <language ident="zh-Hant">Traditional Chinese</language>
            <language ident="zh-Hans">Simplified Chinese</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change n="1.0" when="2018-03-21">CREATED: record</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <entryFree xml:id="k000060" type="building type">
            <term xml:id="term-k000060-5" xml:lang="zh-latn-pinyin-nt" source="#biblk000060-1">ta</term>
            <term xml:id="term-k000060-2" xml:lang="zh-Hant">塔</term>
            <term xml:id="term-k000060-3" xml:lang="zh-Hans">塔</term>
            <term xml:id="term-k000060-4" xml:lang="zh-latn-pinyin" source="#biblk000060-1">tǎ</term>
            <term xml:id="term-k000060-6" xml:lang="zh-latn-wadegile">t`a</term>
            <term xml:id="term-k000060-1" xml:lang="en">pagoda</term>
            <note>
               <p  xml:lang="en">Usually denoting a towering structure containing objects associated with the Buddha or his teachings, the underlying concept behind the Chinese character ta 塔, as well as the etymology of the term, are still debated. Our earliest textual sources suggest that ta was the abbreviation of a transliterated “foreign term” (“barbarian speech” 胡言, “outer states speech” 外國言, “Sanskrit phrase” 梵之稱), likely something akin to “Buddha,” into Chinese characters.  As an architectural form, the ta is a structure organized around a vertical axis and/or spire.</p>
               <p  xml:lang="en" source="#biblk000060-2">The earliest definition of ta we have found comes from the <term ref="/keyword/k000030">Han</term> dynasty <title ref="https://tinyurl.com/ycb7ty9k">Shuowen jiezi 說文解字</title> (Xu Shen 許慎 (ca. 58 – ca. 148 CE)). Here it is defined as a <term >futu 浮屠</term>, a term which, when used in the same text to translate the term <term ref="https://tinyurl.com/2nrpkwh7">seng 僧</term> (Buddhist monk), appears to be a transliteration of the word “buddha” (Xu 1978, 13xia.290; 8shang.168). Textual sources from the second through fifth centuries suggest that ta continued to be linked to other Chinese transliterations of the word “buddha,” or “structure containing a Buddha,” including futu 浮圖, fotu 佛圖, fota 佛塔, and gongta 宮塔. The earliest evidence we have found for transliterations of the Pali term thūpa, which should denote a domical masonry structure containing the relic of the Buddha or (potentially somewhat later) a powerful Buddhist monk (Princeton Dictionary of Buddhism), are toupo 鍮婆 and tapo 塔婆 and are from sutras translated in the fourth-eighth centuries. Sources linking ta to transliterations of the Sanskrit word stupa (such as sutabo 窣塔波 or sudupo 窣堵波), may date back to the sixth century, but are found more commonly from the seventh century and after. Transliterations of  both thupa and stupa appear to refer to structures rather than an individual or belief system.</p>              
               <p>Architecturally speaking, the terms ta and thupa/stupa often denote very different types of objects with the primary unifying characteristics being a central vertical axis and the containment of a sacred Buddhist object. Prior to the fourteenth century, the term ta usually referred to Buddhist structures (Zhang and Luo 1988, 6-7) [Zotero: K3HM3FEE]. Examples of ta found in both physical and textual records indicate a variety of types related to Indic, Central Asian, and Sinitic Buddhist architecture. They generally constituted open-access shrines which could be made of timber or masonry, and which might house iconic images of the Buddha. These include descriptions of multi-storied structures (chonglou 重樓) in sources like the <title ref="https://tinyurl.com/yu3px2mh">Hou Han Shu</title> and objects like the great Bodh Gaya temple, which were referred to in Indic languages with terms such as prasada, vimana, or mandira (Wang Qiming 1988, 410; Meister 1988-89, 256-157)) or domed, masonry structures whose primary sanctifying object was a relic (objects like Stupa 1 at Sanci which were called stupa or caitya in Sanskrit or thupa in Pali).</p>    
               <p>Following Liang Sicheng, research on the architecture of Chinese ta usually emphasizes the taxonomy of structures, describing differences between either multi-story timber frame buildings derived from Han-dynasty towers (including lou 樓 and que 闕), or masonry domed stūpa architecture derived from  Indic models (Liang 2005, 63 Zotero: CDBY89GW). Others aim to locate precedents for multi-storied  timber-framed ta in relic shrines and towering temples found in northern India and Central Asia (Wu Qingzhou 2007, Zhang Gong 1997, Miller 2019, Steinhardt 2014).</p>            
               <p>As a carefully designed container for Buddhist relics (which, by at least the 6th century could include bones, precious stones or metals, or even Buddhist texts), the Sinitic ta, like the Indic stūpa, was a defining focus of rituals across the Buddhist world. In English-language scholarship on Buddhism (and consequently Buddhist art), ta is usually translated as stūpa (or stupa) regardless of the shape of the structure (Princeton Dictionary of Buddhism, entry on stūpa). This may reflect a preference for the use Sanskrit forms of Buddhist terms when translating Chinese Buddhist texts into English (e.g. Boucher used stūpa for ta in his full translation of the Foshuo zaota gongde jing into English, yet there is no Sanskrit original of that text and we thus do not know what Indic term the original author might have had in mind (Boucher 1991, Miller 2019)). It also may reflect the influence of Tang dynasty interpretations of ta, which emphasized the ritual function of ta over its various structural forms (Miller 2019). While some scholars suggest the preservation of relics in dramatic towering containers was intended for commemorative purposes (Seckel 1980, Wang Qiming 1988), or as a foci for Buddhist patronage (Buswell and Lopez, 2013, entry on stupa; Zotero: 2JJM3KWR) others emphasize that relics and their containers across Buddhist Asia were also thought to have thaumaturgic and transformative power (Schopen 1982, E. Wang 2005).  The belief in the thaumaturgic power of the Buddha and his relics was widespread and developed in a multi-lingual, multi-cultural context, with textual descriptions written by religious professionals in elite languages (such as Sanskrit) likely coming later (see Granoff 1996; Copp 2014; Miller 2021). The multiplicity of terms and ambiguity around the appropriate shape for a Buddhist reliquary may thus be a reflection of the different languages of source terms for these objects.</p> 
               <p>By the fourteenth century towering wenfeng ta 文峰塔 (“literary peak” ta) began to be constructed outside the Buddhist context as a means to help rectify deficiencies in the landscape relating to fengshui 風水 practice (Zhang and Luo 1988, 6).  By the twentieth century, the term ta could simply refer to a type of tower, with no religious overtones (e.g. “television tower” dianshita 電視塔).</p>
            </note>
            
         	<idno type="URI">https://architecturasinica.org/keyword/k000060</idno>
            <bibl xml:id="biblk000060-1">
               <ptr target="https://architecturasinica.org/bibl/MLHB8LJF"/>
               <citedRange>accessed May 28, 2022</citedRange>
            </bibl>
            <listBibl xml:id="biblk000060-2">
               <bibl>
                  <ptr target="https://architecturasinica.org/bibl/3VFQDRP"/>
                  <citedRange>accessed May 28, 2022</citedRange>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </entryFree>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>