<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../taxonomy.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xmlns:xd="http://www.oxygenxml.com/ns/doc/xsl" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/"
   xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" xml:lang="zh-latn-pinyin">
               <foreign xml:lang="zh-Hant">雀替</foreign>queti</title>
            <title level="m">Architectura Sinica</title>
            <principal xml:id="TGM">Tracy Miller</principal>
            <editor role="general" ref="#TGM">Tracy Miller</editor>
            <editor role="associate" xml:id="ZJ">ZHUGE Jing 諸葛净</editor>
            <editor role="content-author" xml:id="LZZ">LI Zizi 李孜孜</editor>
            <editor role="content-author" xml:id="BY">BAI Ying  白穎</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Website coordination by</resp>
               <name type="person" xml:id=""></name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Preliminary research and revision: </resp>
               <name type="person" ref="#LZZ">LI Zizi 李孜孜</name>
               <name type="person" ref="#BY">BAI Ying  白穎</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Peer review by</resp>
               <name type="team">ATTCAT 2023-2024</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>English proofreading: </resp>
               <name type="person" xml:id="AC">Aurelia Campbell</name>
               <name type="person" ref="#TGM">Tracy Miller</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Chinese proofreading: </resp>
               <name type="person" ref="#ZJ">ZHUGE Jing 諸葛净</name>
               <name type="person" xml:id="ZLL">ZUO Lala 左拉拉</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data entry: </resp>
               <name type="person" xml:id="FRC">FENG Ruoci 馮若慈</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.0"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Architectura Sinica</authority>
            <idno type="URI">https://architecturasinica.org/keyword/k000287/tei</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2025-05-26-17:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
            <language ident="zh-latn-pinyin">Pinyin</language>
            <language ident="zh-latn-pinyin-nt">Pinyin without tones</language>
            <language ident="zh-latn-wadegile">Wade-Giles</language>
            <language ident="zh-Hant">Traditional Chinese</language>
            <language ident="zh-Hans">Simplified Chinese</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change n="1.0" who="FRC" when="2025-05-26-17:00">CREATED: record</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <entryFree xml:id="k000287" type="architectural feature">
            <term xml:id="term-k000287-1" xml:lang="zh-latn-pinyin-nt">queti</term>
            <term xml:id="term-k000287-2" xml:lang="zh-Hant">雀替</term>
            <term xml:id="term-k000287-3" xml:lang="zh-Hans">雀替</term>
            <term xml:id="term-k000287-4" xml:lang="zh-latn-pinyin">quètì</term>
            <term xml:id="term-k000287-5" xml:lang="zh-latn-wadegile">ch`üeh-t`i</term>
            <term xml:id="term-k000287-6" xml:lang="en" source="#biblk000287-1" >Sparrow brace</term>
            <idno type="URI">https://architecturasinica.org/keyword/k000287</idno>
            <note type="Note">
               <p>under construction</p>
               <p xml:lan="en">Queti 雀替 is a supporting component widely used in Ming and Qing dynasty architecture. Typically positioned at the column tops or integrated with <term ref="/keyword/k000019">dougong</term> (bracket sets), 
                  it supports horizontal members that run parallel to its length. Queti stabilizes the structure by increasing the contact surface area to protect the joint. In official <term ref="/keyword/k000051">Ming</term> and <term ref="/keyword/k000070">Qing</term> 
                  architecture, the queti developed a standardized form characterized by cloud-like curved bases and oblique ends. When installed symmetrically on both sides of a pillar, its appearance 
                  resembles a bird with spread wings. Queti are usually combined with other decorative components, which are specified in official regulations. （Wang et al. 1993, 22; Qinggongbu 1734, 28.30a) </p>
               <p xml:lan="en">Structurally, queti can be classified into two main categories. The first type, “separable” queti, is the most prevalent form. In separable queti, a tenon joint at one end 
                  is inserted into the pillar, while nails at the top affix the queti to horizontal members (see illustration). The second type is “integral” queti, which either penetrates through the pillar 
                  body or, when used in dougong partitions, rests atop the cap block (<term ref="/keyword/k000158">ludou</term>) and connects to upper members via nails or hidden tenons. This type of queti functions similarly to timu, but has 
                  a different shape.The term queti appears in historical texts on official architecture using a number of different characters and names, for example 雀替 (queti), 鵲替 (queti), 榱題 (cuiti), 
                  or 雀木 (quemu). </p>
               <p xml:lan="en">Contemporary scholarship, notably influenced by Liang Sicheng's work, sometimes refers to queti as jiaoti 角替—a usage possibly stemming from Liang's miswriting that has 
                  influenced subsequent research. Liang categorized queti into seven types based on extant examples. His  classification broadened the concept to encompass Tibetan architectural tuomu and 
                  Ming-Qing royal building decorative elements, such as hua yazi (see illustration). Building on Liang's research, contemporary scholars have explored the nomenclature, morphology, 
                  structural functions, and origins of queti. The term's semantic scope has evolved from its historical usage, with some scholars narrowly defining it as the wooden support for <term ref="/keyword/k000115">efang</term> or 
                  lan'e at the column tops, while others extending its use more broadly. （Liang 1936, 4-5; Guo 2005, 183-184; Gao 2009; Zhuang and Hu 2007) </p> 
               <p xml:lang="zh-Hant">“雀替”指明清建築中的一種承托構件，常用於柱上端，或與枓拱組合以承托上方與雀替長平行的水平構件，通過加大接觸面，保護其上水平構件與柱間節點，維護結構穩定性。雀替輪廓在明清官式建築中形成了一種較為
                  固定的形式，下部作雲曲線，端頭作斜直線。于柱左右設置時如鳥雀展翅。在清官式建築中，雀替通常與其它裝飾性構件結合。（王璞子等,1993，22; 清工部 1734，28.30a)</p>
               <p xml:lang="zh-Hant">雀替構造方式可分為兩類。一、分件式雀替，通常一端開榫插於柱內，上方用釘與水準構件相連，為最常見做法。此外，當柱間距較近時兩塊雀替連做為“騎馬雀替”時，或三檁垂花門中做假素雀替時，“雀替”兩端開榫，
                  插於兩端柱內。二、整體式雀替。用於枓栱隔架科中，騎於枓上。以釘或暗銷與上方構件相連。用於柱上時，穿過柱身。此種雀替作用與清代插入柱中的替木相似，但使用特定的樣式。</p>
               <p xml:lang="zh-Hant">“雀替”也寫作“鵲替”、“榱題”、“雀木”，主要見於清官式建築文獻記載。（“鵲替”一詞最早見於明萬歷四十三年(1615年)《工部廠庫須知12卷》中琉璃作“花鵲替”。“雀替”一詞最早記載於清代《內庭木石油裱現行則例不
                  分卷》，至遲為雍正九年三月十五日（1731年）。同书于“门殿雕工则”中写作“雀木”。）</p>
               <p xml:lang="zh-Hant">明清文獻中根據不同的雕刻、組合方式，有大雀替、龍門雀替、雀替、小雀替（雕作）；雲拱雀替、素雀替、假素雀替連墊拱板（組合方式）等不同做法。根據材料不同，有仿木琉璃構件，有“花雀替”和“雀替枓科”等称法。
                  石构建筑实物中，还常见仿木的石雀替。）</p>
               <p xml:lang="zh-Hant">現代研究者也称“雀替”为“角替”，可能为梁思成误写 （梁思成，1934，79），影响部分学者（馬炳堅 1991,194；高陽，2009,76；王效青等，1996,350））。梁思成结合实物，将雀替分为七种，即大雀替、龙门雀替、
                  雀替、小雀替、通雀替、骑马雀替和花牙子（梁思成，1936，2）。在这一分類中，雀替指代的范围扩大，包括了藏式建筑中的托木、明清官式建筑装修作中的花牙子。之後學者基於梁思成的研究，對雀替命名、形式、結構功能和溯源展開討論
                  （梁思成，1936，4-5，8-9；郭華瑜，2005，183-184；）。術語“雀替”指代範圍相較基於古代文献所理解的範圍，发生了语义的偏移。部分學者將雀替片面地理解為柱子上端承托額枋（或闌額）的木構件；部分学者則扩大化地认为雀替
                  的范围包括罩、撑栱、牛腿等。（高 2009；庄和胡 2007）</p>  
            </note>
            <bibl xml:id="biblk000287-1">
               <ptr target="https://architecturasinica.org/bibl/MIIQ4VBC"/>
            </bibl>
            <listRelation>
               <relation ref="skos:broadMatch" active="https://architecturasinica.org/keyword/k000287" passive="bracketing"/>
            </listRelation>
         </entryFree>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
